<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://bokaixu.site/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://bokaixu.site/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-12-07T06:09:01+00:00</updated><id>https://bokaixu.site/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Bokai Xu’s Blog</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">蓝色监狱</title><link href="https://bokaixu.site/blog/2024/blue-hell/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="蓝色监狱"/><published>2024-10-05T00:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-05T00:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://bokaixu.site/blog/2024/blue-hell</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bokaixu.site/blog/2024/blue-hell/"><![CDATA[<p>去深圳探望（或者投奔）我的朋友 h。h 说自己正在蓝色监狱服刑不能出远门，因此不能和我去福田或者罗湖吃饭了。h 说他的脊柱被植入了定位芯片，但芯片是他的另一个人格注入的。</p> <p>一个蓝色的监狱</p> <p>一颗火红的心</p> <p>黑色的眼珠</p> <p>有着白色的恐惧</p> <p>h 说，我是除了他父母外给帮助他最多的人。我也想对他说同样的话。</p> <p>自我反省或静下来思考是一个很有趣的事情，很多事情在半夜一点钟从下园走三十分钟的盘山公路回宿舍的路上都清楚的显现出来，或者消失的无影无踪了。这真的是一个令人充满电的活动。</p> <p>让 h 测荣格八维，他拒绝测。我读给他听他都懒得听。</p> <blockquote> <p>-晚上不如就吃昨天的肉卷吧 -估计已经在垃圾场了 -啊？不是…我要留着夜宵的啊 -你来图书馆了吗 我在四楼 -我在昨天 -那你可以现在去那个垃圾桶 把肉卷捡回来</p> </blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="thoughts"/><category term="thoughts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[去深圳探望（或者投奔）我的朋友 h。h 说自己正在蓝色监狱服刑不能出远门，因此不能和我去福田或者罗湖吃饭了。h 说他的脊柱被植入了定位芯片，但芯片是他的另一个人格注入的。]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Recent Reflections II</title><link href="https://bokaixu.site/blog/2024/reflections-oct/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Recent Reflections II"/><published>2024-10-02T00:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-02T00:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://bokaixu.site/blog/2024/reflections-oct</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bokaixu.site/blog/2024/reflections-oct/"><![CDATA[<p>Long time no see. Sometimes I feel that I’ve made some connections to the world again… I am alive again…</p> <p>But the difficulties still present. I dream about good things, but the reality is not good. Work has to be done, and life has to go on. I tried to analyze myself and others. That makes me feel really good.</p> <p>To write some texts without any interruptions, is really good.</p> <p>I missed the year of 2020. It was golden. Now I finally got some feelings of 2020.</p> <p>Thank you, my friend.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="thoughts"/><category term="thoughts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Long time no see. Sometimes I feel that I’ve made some connections to the world again… I am alive again…]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflections on Grokking</title><link href="https://bokaixu.site/blog/2024/reflection-on-grokking/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflections on Grokking"/><published>2024-05-04T00:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-04T00:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://bokaixu.site/blog/2024/reflection-on-grokking</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bokaixu.site/blog/2024/reflection-on-grokking/"><![CDATA[<p>Grokking is really intriguing, not only in training models. I found that I have kept eating vegetables as dinner for over two weeks. I found it boring and it makes me hungry and unhappy during the night. But I am a person who dislikes to choose different foods from a variety of choices each day, so to eat the same thing for a long time seems to be less stressful and make me happier. I found that I seems to lose some weight suddenly. That’s weired.</p> <p>So, I think I am grokking. A few days ago, I used a hard dataset to train MiniCPM-V-2.0, and I observed that the loss keeps decreasing, but the slope is small, and the accuracy is always 0. That’s so weired. But after about an hour (about 50 steps of training), the grokking happened. The loss sharply decreases and the accuracy shot up to about 70%.</p> <p>I think there are some similarity between eating vegetables and grokking in model training. It can’t be observed temperally, but finally it works. The mechanism is hard to explain, and I haven’t got an answer.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="thoughts"/><category term="thoughts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Grokking is really intriguing, not only in training models. I found that I have kept eating vegetables as dinner for over two weeks. I found it boring and it makes me hungry and unhappy during the night. But I am a person who dislikes to choose different foods from a variety of choices each day, so to eat the same thing for a long time seems to be less stressful and make me happier. I found that I seems to lose some weight suddenly. That’s weired.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflections on Statistics</title><link href="https://bokaixu.site/blog/2024/reflection-on-statistics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflections on Statistics"/><published>2024-04-23T00:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-23T00:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://bokaixu.site/blog/2024/reflection-on-statistics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bokaixu.site/blog/2024/reflection-on-statistics/"><![CDATA[<p>Today, while working on a statistics assignment, I found an answer on Google for a question that has been around since 2004. It made me wonder why, despite many years of progress in statistics, no teacher ever told me:</p> <ol> <li> <p>The normal distribution can be described using only the first and second moments; third moments or higher are not needed. This means that the first and second moments are sufficient statistics for data that follows a normal distribution.</p> </li> <li> <p>When we assume data follows a normal distribution, we can derive the distributions for any necessary metrics from the normal distribution itself. These metrics depend heavily on human intuition and can often be defined arbitrarily. Once a metric is defined, its distribution can likely be deduced, allowing for hypothesis testing.</p> </li> <li> <p>All tools in linear regression rely on the assumption that residuals follow a normal distribution. If the residuals followed a Laplace distribution, these tools would not hold. But why must residuals follow a normal distribution? Perhaps it’s because many unconsidered variables exist, and the average or linear combination of numerous variables results in a normal distribution. Including more variables can reduce the absolute value of residuals.</p> </li> </ol> <p>Is it possible that the founders of statistical inference valued these assumptions, but over years of tradition, they became less emphasized?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="thoughts"/><category term="thoughts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today, while working on a statistics assignment, I found an answer on Google for a question that has been around since 2004. It made me wonder why, despite many years of progress in statistics, no teacher ever told me:]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Explain Young People’s Creativity</title><link href="https://bokaixu.site/blog/2024/young-people-creativity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Explain Young People’s Creativity"/><published>2024-04-15T00:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-15T00:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://bokaixu.site/blog/2024/young-people-creativity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bokaixu.site/blog/2024/young-people-creativity/"><![CDATA[<p>The creativity of young people seems hard to perceive when I was a high school student. I learned that Einstein created his Relativity when he was 24. Now I finally understand, to make contributions in one’s own field, one need to make his/her mind in specific environment and develop representations about the subject first. This process takes time, and it is hard for someone to switch to a different field in a short period of time. This is the shift of representations, or more intuitively, the shift of the ability of discrepency.</p> <p>Representations of data is important. One need to discriminate all the concepts in a subject to make derivation between different concepts and entities. So, a good representation is the foundation of creativity.</p> <p>To develop a good representation in a specific field, one need to construct basic and simple concepts first. Built upon basic operations, it is possible to make deeper representations about more difficult concepts using previous representations. For human, it is normal to learn basic knowledge first, and learn harder knowledge later. For LLMs, it may have a learning-frontier, just like the diagram in <a href="https://lilianweng.github.io/posts/2024-02-05-human-data-quality/#:~:text=Fig.%2011.%20Data%20map%20for%20SNLI%20training%20set%2C%20based%20on%20a%20RoBERTa%20classifier.%20(Image%20source%3A%20Swayamdipta%20et%20al.%202020)">Lilian Weng’s blog about data quality</a>. Data at the frontier will be continously learned - or have the fastest rate of learning.</p> <p>As is mentioned by Ilya, to understand is the most important part in LLMs, generation of next token is not that important.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="thoughts"/><category term="thoughts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The creativity of young people seems hard to perceive when I was a high school student. I learned that Einstein created his Relativity when he was 24. Now I finally understand, to make contributions in one’s own field, one need to make his/her mind in specific environment and develop representations about the subject first. This process takes time, and it is hard for someone to switch to a different field in a short period of time. This is the shift of representations, or more intuitively, the shift of the ability of discrepency.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Recent Reflections</title><link href="https://bokaixu.site/blog/2024/reflections/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Recent Reflections"/><published>2024-03-25T00:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-25T00:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://bokaixu.site/blog/2024/reflections</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bokaixu.site/blog/2024/reflections/"><![CDATA[<p>A close friend of mine is an INTJ. He mentioned having an N score of over 90%, and I’ve always enjoyed our conversations since we met. I appreciate forming connections with individuals who are intuitive. Recently, I’ve been working on training embedding models, and I’m particularly interested in replicating intuitivity with language models. Their unique perspectives often contribute unexpectedly helpful solutions to problems.</p> <p>I’m not fond of the competitive nature often described as involution, where those with ample resources don’t contribute meaningfully – I mean, productivity improvement.</p> <p>There are those who take pride in their work in discrete optimization, such as designing convolutional kernels manually or empirical rules, considering themselves as refined thinkers. However, it might be beneficial for them to focus more on meta learning.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="thoughts"/><category term="thoughts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A close friend of mine is an INTJ. He mentioned having an N score of over 90%, and I’ve always enjoyed our conversations since we met. I appreciate forming connections with individuals who are intuitive. Recently, I’ve been working on training embedding models, and I’m particularly interested in replicating intuitivity with language models. Their unique perspectives often contribute unexpectedly helpful solutions to problems.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Identifying Habitual Thoughts</title><link href="https://bokaixu.site/blog/2023/identify-thoughts/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Identifying Habitual Thoughts"/><published>2023-12-18T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-18T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://bokaixu.site/blog/2023/identify-thoughts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bokaixu.site/blog/2023/identify-thoughts/"><![CDATA[<p>I learned how to identify those thoughts that we have got used to, from a friend, during 1 year’s time. He is genius in analytic philosophy. To think about conciousness and symbolization of people in society/institutions.</p> <p>The naming of a person is the beginning of symbolization. Under the context of symbolization, life is precious to some extent. Without such symbolization, it is possible to view every individual similar to animals. In such case, to die is not scaring anymore.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="thoughts"/><category term="thoughts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I learned how to identify those thoughts that we have got used to, from a friend, during 1 year’s time. He is genius in analytic philosophy. To think about conciousness and symbolization of people in society/institutions.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Probing Conciousness with Multimodal Long-Context Large Language Models</title><link href="https://bokaixu.site/blog/2023/llm-agents/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Probing Conciousness with Multimodal Long-Context Large Language Models"/><published>2023-12-15T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-15T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://bokaixu.site/blog/2023/llm-agents</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bokaixu.site/blog/2023/llm-agents/"><![CDATA[<p>In my Cognitive Psychology course at CUHK(SZ) — for which I received a grade of C+ — I was first introduced to the concept of <em>perception</em>. It’s a fascinating property found in myriad entities. For instance, after pretraining, a Vision Transformer can “perceive” a <em>cat</em> within its embeddings. The property also exists in many creatures (insects, cats, dogs, human).</p> <p>I frequently muse about the essence of <em>human consciousness</em>—potentially defined as the brain’s perception of its existence. It’s a property absent in many entities. Take a bottle, for instance. Can it perceive its existence? This form of consciousness varies among beings—comparable in mammals, yet distinct in insects. I’m curious: if we were to replicate such a brain structure using VISOR and extract circuits using Deep Learning, and then program these networks to process signals, what could be the outcome?</p> <p>On a parallel note, imagine using a large language model paired with vision or environmental encoders and external devices. If this model had an extensive context capacity (like 1,000,000+ tokens) to retain daily information, and if trained to embed these memories into its parameters, what could be the possibilities? And, the objective function, should be somewhat like uncertainty, because neurons prefer a predictable stimulus, rather than a random stimulus.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="thoughts"/><category term="thoughts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Imagine using a large language model paired with vision or environmental encoders and external devices.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Explanation for Conciousness</title><link href="https://bokaixu.site/blog/2023/cliques-conciousness/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Explanation for Conciousness"/><published>2023-11-01T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-01T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://bokaixu.site/blog/2023/cliques-conciousness</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://bokaixu.site/blog/2023/cliques-conciousness/"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I came across an explanation for <em>conciousness</em> in cerebral cortex. The cortex, could be represented by multiple neuron cliques, each clique could encode a type of unique feeling, and these cliques could be varying, that means, during learning, the cliques and the number of cliques could change. When multiple cliques activates simutanuously, it could produce different combinations of feelings, that becomes the conciousness. Just like the hidden states of a large language model, usually 4096 dimensional, could represent the overall semantic for a sentence or a passage. But now the problem is, how do we perceive our own existence? That could be a problem… But the perception of our own existence could also be a type of feeling (semantic) composed by a combination of neuron cliques. So, that could provide a possible explanation of conciousness defined above. And the human awareness is nothing different from other mammals or insects. It is just because insects’ brain is not complex enought to perceive their own existence. But the perception is the same.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="thoughts"/><category term="thoughts"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I proposed an explanation for conciousness in cerebral cortex, building a link between language models and human brains.]]></summary></entry></feed>